so where we left off in the last video, where Benjamin Franklin was born, to appear the tenth son, to a Puritan father, of Boston...
working for his brother as an apprentice at age twelve, but then runs away at seventeen
right he runs away he had written the silence do good essays
him writing these Soutine silence due good but Franklin didn't want to remain an apprentice even though he was bound do to so
Night time, he gets on a boat in Boston, sails originally to New York and after a few
is to continue on to philadelphia going up the uhh the philadelphia bay, the deleware bay and into the river, and onto the market
[Voice 1]: ...of Philadelphia and there's a famous scene of him arriving [Voice 2]: this is seventeen years old, young kid [Voice 1] seventeen years old, bedraggled, wet...
He has only a few coins in his pocket, as he arrives at the wharf he gives one of the coins to the boat man as a tip, he says when you're really poor
People don't know you're poor, so you pretend to be a little bit richer, so there it is Franklin already caring about his public relations, uhh
sort of being a typical American, saying I don't want to look like I'm poor, I'm going to be a generous guy marching up Market Street
off he rolls and he's all wet and bedraggled. He passes a doorway and there's a fifteen year old girl named Deborah Reid.
and she sort of laughs at him, thinks he makes a ridiculous looking figure. Now we know this because years later